So the good news is that this is the very final video about data set curation.
좋은 소식은 이게 데이터 세트 큐레이션에 관한 마지막 영상이라는 거예요
You were probably fed up of data set curation.
데이터 세트 큐레이션이 지겨웠을 거예요
Now there's just one more piece and then we are done.
이제 하나만 더 하면 끝이에요
So we have crafted an outstanding data set of which we should be very proud.
그래서 우린 아주 훌륭한 데이터 세트를 만들었어요 아주 자랑스럽게 여겨야 하죠
Let's do some final peeks at it.
마지막으로 살짝 보죠
Um, one question that you might ask.
궁금한 게 하나 있어요
Um, well, I'm going to ask it anyway.
그래도 물어볼 거예요
Is is it possible that the price of an item is related?
물건의 가격과 관련이 있을까요?
It's correlated to how long the description is of that item.
물건의 길이에 따라 관련이 있어요
You might imagine a situation where the higher price things tend to have more information.
가격이 높은 물건일수록 정보가 더 많은 상황을 상상할 수 있죠
And that would be worth us understanding.
그걸 이해해야 해요
Um, because yeah, that's something that the model would learn from quickly.
모델에게 그런 걸 빨리 배울 수 있거든요
And it gives us a good sense, perhaps when we look at traditional approaches about how we might approach
어떻게 접근할지 전통적인 접근법을 보면 좋은 감이 오죠
it.
이건 멋진 산란도예요 엑스 축의 개별 크기를 보여줄 거예요
It's going to show us the length of the description, and on the y axis it's going to show us the price.
설명의 길이를 보여줄 거예요 y축에서는 가격을 보여주고요
Um, let's have a look at this across the full sample data set.
전체 샘플 데이터 세트를 살펴보죠
So here we go.
자, 시작하죠
Here's a nice nice picture for you.
여기 잘 나온 사진이 있어요
So there are 400,000 points on this picture.
이 그림에는 400,000점이 있어요
Uh and it's something to look at.
볼거리도 많고요
You can see in it there's there's a lot to digest.
보시다시피 소화할 게 많아요
You can see this interesting pattern that's happening as prices tend to be more prevalent at these boundary
흥미로운 패턴이 일어나고 있어요 가격이 이런 경계선에서 더 자주 나타나죠
points.
799달러짜리 상품도 있고요 보다시피 더 저렴한 제품도 많아요
And you can see that there is something of apparently a correlation that, uh, items which have longer
분명히 상관관계가 있는 게 보이실 거예요 설명이 긴 물건들은 때때로
descriptions do appear, perhaps sometimes to have a trend of being the more expensive ones.
더 비싼 물건이라는 추세를 보이는 거죠
But it's not clear that there's a significant correlation in that regard.
하지만 그 일과 관련해서 중요한 상관관계가 있는지는 확실하지 않아요
So there's something there, but it's nothing major.
뭔가 있긴 한데 심각한 건 아니에요
So we suspect that traditional machine learning, when trying to look at something like that will probably
전통적인 머신 러닝을 적용하면 큰 상관관계를
not find any major correlation.
찾지 못할 거예요
So just an example of the kind of, um, diagram that you can come up with to try and get insight into
일종의 다이어그램을 예로 들게요 데이터의 다양한 양상에 대한 통찰력을 얻기
different aspects of your data.
위한 거죠 Get it
One other thing I want to talk about for a moment more is tokens.
잠시 더 얘기하고 싶은 건 토큰이에요
Um, and uh, the, um, we're going to be working a lot more with tokens when we get to actually training
오픈 소스 모델에 대해 실제로 훈련하게 되면 Get 토큰으로 더 많이 작업할 겁니다
against an open source model, but it's worth looking at tokens right now.
지금 토큰을 살펴볼 가치가 있어요
So I've just written this function report, which takes an item and which will then print, uh, the
함수 리포트를 작성했는데 아이템을 하나 가져와서 프롬프트를 프린트합니다
prompt, first of all, the full training prompt that will be used during training.
훈련 때 사용될 전체 훈련 프롬프트죠
And then the last ten tokens in that prompt, and then it will decode those.
마지막 10개의 토큰을 프롬프트에 입력하면 디코딩이 되는 것이죠
So we'll see the bits of text that map to the last ten tokens.
마지막 10개의 토큰까지의 행적을 볼 수 있어요
And if you're wondering why the last ten you're going to see in just a second.
왜 마지막 10개가 있는지 궁금하시다면 잠시 후에 보여드리죠
So let's pick a random number, number 40,000 and run this.
무작위로 40,000번을 선택해 실행해보죠
Okay.
네
So this here sorry for all of this text here.
여기 이건∙∙∙ 여기 있는 텍스트 전부 죄송해요
That is the prompt that's going to be sent to the LLM to learn from.
LLM으로 보내져 배울 수 있는 프롬프트죠
Um, it's going to be asked how much does this cost to the nearest dollar.
최대한 비용이 많이 들 거라고 할 거예요
And then it's going to get a description.
그런 다음 설명을 get 하죠
And then price is and then this which is the price rounded to the nearest dollar.
가격은 이겁니다 가격은 1달러로 반올림한 거고요
You'll note if you look in the item code that when building the training prompt, it rounds this to
아이템 코드를 보시면 훈련 프롬프트를 만들 때 가장 가까운 달러로 회전하는 것을
the nearest dollar.
알 수 있죠
So if we look at the last ten tokens you can see what's happening here I'm printing out underneath it.
마지막 10개의 토큰을 보면 어떻게 된 건지 알 수 있죠 아래에 프린트했어요
What are those ten tokens.
그 10패는 뭐죠?
And I just wanted to show you that in terms of the final few tokens, price gets mapped to one token
이제 마지막 몇 개의 토큰을 보여드릴게요 가격은 하나의 토큰에 매핑되고
is gets a token with that start of of of word space before it dollars again with the start of word,
워드 스페이스의 시작을 가진 토큰을 받습니다 워드의 시작과 함께 달러의 시작을 가진 토큰이죠
and then the number 34 is getting mapped to one specific token.
그리고 숫자 34는 하나의 특정 토큰에 매핑되고요
And this is, as I say, just a feature of the llama tokenizer that it does.
이건 라마 토큰라이저의 기능 중 하나예요
As with GPT, it does have a separate token for every three digit number.
GPT처럼 세 자리 숫자마다 토큰을 갖고 있어요
Some of the other tokenizers the other models do not.
다른 모델의 토큰이 그렇지 않은 경우도 있어요
Um, and whilst this isn't required for our project, it does make things a bit simpler for us later.
우리 프로젝트에 필수적인 건 아니지만 나중에 비트를 보면 좀 더 간단해질 거예요
And then the period gets one token and the .00 gets one token.
마침표는 토큰 하나와 더불어∙∙∙ 더불어∙∙∙ 0은 토큰을 받아요
Let's do another sample.
샘플을 하나 더 해 보죠
Let's do something completely, uh, something in a different location altogether.
완전히 다른 장소에서 뭔가 해 보자고요
Number 10,000.
10,000번요
And this is a something that's rather cheap.
이건 가격이 저렴해요
It costs $9 and price is 9000.
9천 달러인데 가격이 9천 달러예요
Let's go for something that's near the end of the data set 398,000.
데이터셋 398,000의 끝에 있는 것으로 가보죠
And this is a, um, uh, coilover damper kit.
이건 코일오버 댐퍼 키트예요
And this price is $765.
가격은 765달러예요
And you'll see once more that the 765 gets mapped to one token.
또 한 번 765가 토큰 하나에 매핑되는 걸 보실 수 있어요
So you should satisfy yourself this this sample is of course sorted by cheapest first ish because we've
이제 만족하셔야 해요 이 샘플은 가장 싼 것부터 분류했어요 각
gone through sampling, uh, in each, each category.
항목의 샘플을 다 살펴봤거든요
So, so rounded to the nearest dollar.
가장 가까운 달러로 동그랗게 돌려요
It is sorted by cheapest in the lower, um, parts of the sample, and the most expensive in the higher
가장 싼 제품은 낮은 제품군으로 분류하고 가장 비싼 제품은 높은 제품군으로
parts of the sample.
분류해요
And you can satisfy yourself that we are getting this effect, that every number from 1 to 999 is getting
이렇게 효과를 얻는다고 만족하실 수 있습니다 1부터 999까지의 숫자는 모두 토큰 하나에
mapped to one token, just as it says here.
매핑됩니다 여기 나와 있는 것처럼요
And as I say one more time, when, uh, look at the quantity or gamma or phi three tokenizers, you'll
다시 한번 말씀드리지만 수량이나 감마 혹은 피 쓰리 토큰라이저를 보면 그렇지 않다는
see that that's not the case.
걸 알 수 있어요
Um, it turns out to be a little bit handy for us later on, but it's not required and definitely later.
나중에 비트가 좀 유용할 것 같긴 한데 꼭 필요한 건 아니고 나중엔 꼭 필요해요
If you want to experiment with using other models like Quantum Gemini three, you can simply switch
양자 제미니 3호 같은 다른 모델을 실험하고 싶다면 스위치만
it in and it will work.
켜면 돼요
You'll just find here that it will be mapped to multiple tokens, not to the one token for the three
여기 보면 여러 개의 토큰에 매핑되어 있습니다. 하나의 3자리 토큰이 아니라요.
Okay, big sigh of relief.
안도의 한숨을 내쉬네요
We've made it through data curation.
데이터 큐레이션을 통과했어요
The last part of it all is to finish things off and upload to the hub.
마지막 단계는 마무리하고 허브에 업로드 하는 거죠
And what we're going to do to start with is shuffle up our data set, because it's no good at all if
가장 먼저 할 일은 데이터 세트를 섞는 겁니다 가장 싼 순서대로 분류하면
it's sorted in order of cheapest.
전혀 좋지 않으니까요
First we need a nice jumbled data set.
먼저 잘 뒤섞인 데이터 집합이 필요해요
Um, and first I, um, set the random seed because I want to make sure that we always are working with
먼저 무작위 씨앗을 설정했어요 항상 정확히 같은 데이터로 작업하도록 확실히 하려고요
exactly the same data set so that you can reproduce exactly the same stuff that I will and get the same
그래야 제가 하려는 것과 정확히 같은 걸 복제해서 같은 결과를 얻을 수 있으니까요 get
outcomes.
it
Um, we use Random.shuffle to shuffle things up, and then I take the first 400,000 as my training data
랜덤을 사용해요 섞어서 섞은 다음 첫 400,000개를 훈련 데이터로 가져가요
set.
그 다음 2000년은 테스트 세트죠
Now I hear you.
이제 알겠어요
You cry, you data scientists.
데이터 과학자들은 울죠
That one normally takes, like, at least a 5% or 10% test data set here.
보통 테스트 데이터는 최소 5%에서 10%가 필요해요
Um, and you can absolutely feel free to do so because obviously we've got we've got 8000 data points
얼마든지 그렇게 하셔도 돼요 여기 데이터 포인트가 8,000개
right, right here.
있거든요
And you can also, of course, sample more to have a bigger data set.
더 많은 샘플을 채취해 더 큰 데이터를 얻을 수도 있죠
It won't be necessary for us because we're going to find that we're only going to use a few hundred
우리한테는 필요 없을 거예요 왜냐하면 테스트에 몇백 개만 사용할 거니까요
And that's going to give us very accurate results.
그럼 아주 정확한 결과가 나오죠
And we get diminishing returns if we keep testing against more and more.
계속 더 많이 시험하면 결과도 감소하죠 Get it
So this is plenty for our purposes for this project, but it is a best practice.
이 프로젝트의 목적에는 충분하지만 최선의 관행이죠
I don't know if it's a best practice.
최선의 관행인지는 모르겠어요
It's a common practice to reserve at least 5% of these other, uh, for the test data set, and sometimes
일반적인 관행은 적어도 5%를 테스트 데이터 집합에 비축하는 것이고 때로는 5%를
to to separately have 5% for test and a 5% for validation, as I talked about before.
테스트에 비축하고 5%를 유효성 검증에 비축하는 것이죠
Um, not required for this purpose, but by all means, you can do it if you wish and have that as an
이 목적에는 필요 없지만 원한다면 얼마든지 할 수 있어요 관리할 추가 데이터
extra data set that you manage.
집합으로 가질 수 있죠
Um, but anyway, we will do that.
어쨌든 그렇게 할 거예요
We will jumble it up.
전부 뒤섞을 거예요
It's been divided into a training dataset of 400,000 and a test set of 2000.
훈련 데이터 400,000개와 테스트 세트 2000개로 나뉘었죠
Let's have a look at the first the the the test first element.
그럼 첫 번째 테스트 요소를 보죠
The test prompt that you remember is the prompt without revealing the answer.
여러분이 기억하는 테스트 프롬프트는 답을 공개하지 않은 프롬프트죠
This is the prompt that will be sent to sorry, I'm looking at the training prompt first, then we'll
이게 전송될 프롬프트∙∙∙ 죄송합니다 훈련 프롬프트를 먼저 보고 테스트 프롬프트를
look at the test prompt.
보죠
The training prompt is the one that does have the answer.
훈련 시기가 해답을 갖고 있어요
So the training prompt says how much does this cost to the nearest dollar.
훈련용 문자가 가장 가까운 비용으로 얼마가 드는지를 보여주죠
It is a Delphi fuel pump module.
델포이 연료 펌프 모듈이에요
Um, and uh yeah.
그리고 네
How about that.
어때요?
It costs $227.
227달러예요
I would have had no clue about that.
전 전혀 몰랐을 거예요
So this is an example of something that will be sent to an LM as part of training, because it contains
이건 훈련의 일부로 LM으로 보내질 것의 예입니다 설명과
the description and it contains the price.
가격이 포함돼 있거든요
Um, so let's look at a test prompt.
테스트 프롬프트를 보죠
Now the test prompt is going to show us something that will be used, which will have the description,
테스트 프롬프트는 사용될 뭔가를 보여줄 겁니다 설명은 있지만
but it will not have the price.
가격은 없죠
And this is the first item in our test set.
이게 테스트 세트의 첫 번째 항목이에요
So there we have it.
자, 됐어요
Uh, let's have a quick look at the distribution of prices for the first 250 test points, because these
첫 250가지 테스트 포인트들의 가격 분배를 빠르게 살펴봅시다. 왜냐하면 이 포인트들은 모델
are actually the points that we'll be using most of the time for actually testing our model.
테스트에 가장 많이 사용되는 포인트들이거든요.
And you can see there's a nice healthy spread of different prices here.
다양한 가격대가 잘 분포돼 있어요
There's plenty of things in the higher area that will test whether the model can handle expensive things.
높은 영역에서는 이 모델이 비싼 물건을 다룰 수 있는지 테스트할 것들이 많아요
And then, you know, the majority are the cheaper priced with a good variety of prices in our test
그리고 다수가 저렴한 제품으로 테스트 데이터에 다양한 가격대가 포함되어
data set.
있죠
Okay, finally, finally, we now turn this into a series of training prompts and test prompts, uh,
자, 마지막으로 이제 이걸 일련의 훈련과 테스트 프롬프트로 바꿀게요
which is just simply plucking out the the prompt and the test prompt that we just looked at, along
방금 본 테스트 프롬프트와 가격표를 뽑아내는 거죠
This little piece of code here will upload it to the hugging face.
이 코드는 포옹하는 얼굴에 업로드 돼요
I will turn it into a data set object suitable for the hugging face hub, by calling the Fromdict for
안는 얼굴 허브에 적합한 데이터셋 객체로 바꿀 겁니다 데이터셋에 대한 Fromex를 호출하고
a data set and then putting that into a data set dict.
dataset 독감에 넣는 거죠
And then finally this line here will upload your data set to the Hugging Face hub so that you can continue
마지막으로 이 라인은 데이터 세트를 안아주는 페이스 허브에 업로드 합니다 계속 사용하거나
to use it and download it for future.
앞으로 다운로드 할 수 있도록요
Uh, when we get to to fine tuning, uh, but I'm not going to run it because I've already run it.
get me fine 튜닝이 끝나면요 하지만 이미 작동했으니 실행하진 않을 거예요
And this is for you to put in your username.
그리고 이건 당신의 사용자이름을 입력하세요.
I have this uploaded to to my to to uh, um, sorry, I have it uploaded to my username here.
업로드해 놨어요, 제 어, 죄송합니다 제 사용자 이름에 업로드해 놨어요
So you will be able to also just retrieve the data that way too.
그렇게 데이터를 검색할 수도 있어요
If you wanted to short circuit all of this data curation, which hopefully you do not want to do.
이 모든 데이터 큐레이션을 합선시키고 싶다면요 그런 일은 없길 바라지만요
Um, and then as a final thing here, um, I'm going to turn this train and test the collection into
마지막으로 이 기차를 돌려서 피클 파일로 만들어 볼게요
I'm going to pickle it and put it into a file so we can load it for future days so we don't have to
절여서 파일에 넣을 거예요 앞으로 로드할 수 있게요 목록 작성하는
go through all of this rigmarole again of building our lists.
이 복잡한 과정을 다시 거칠 필요가 없도록요
So if you're familiar with Python pickles, it's super easy way to take a Python object and dump it
파이썬 을 잘 아신다면 파이썬 을 파일에 덤프하는 아주 쉬운 방법이에요
And now that I've run that, there will be two new files here test dot pickle and train dot pickle that
이제 실행하면 새 파일이 두 개 생기죠 test.pickle과 Tack.pickle이요
will contain my training and test data set.
트레이닝과 테스트 데이터 세트를 포함하죠
And with that we have completed our data curation work.
이로써 데이터 큐레이션을 마쳤어요
Please can I leave with you to investigate the data set more and to also confirm when you try out this,
데이터 집합을 더 살펴보고 확인하기 위해 이 작업을 진행할 텐데요. 서로
this exercise of trying to tokenize, uh, different, um, uh, different data points that you always
다른 데이터 포인트를 토큰화하는 작업입니다. 그러면 항상 세 자릿수가 하나의
get the case that three digit numbers tokenized to one token and get a sense for those tokens.
토큰으로 토큰화되고 토큰의 감각을 얻을 수 있죠.
And with that, I will see you back with the slides for a wrap up.
그럼 마무리로 슬라이드로 다시 만나죠